Guide to the Thomas E. McCollough Papers, 1965-1997
Duke University. University Archives
Thomas E. McCollough papers 1965-1997
Duke University. University Archives
McCollough, Thomas Elmore, 1926-.
3 linear feet Extent: 2,000 Items
Thomas McCollough was a professor of religion at Duke University from 1961-1997. His collection includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, course materials, and other papers relating to the Religion Department, the Twentieth Century American Program, university-related committees, and other activities. The collection ranges in date from 1965-1997.
RL.01698
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
Provenance
The Thomas E. McCollough Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1998.
Biographical Note
Thomas McCollough was born in Birmingham, Alabama and grew up in Texas, Georgia and New Mexico. He served in the Navy V-12 Training Program and earned his B.B.A. degree from the University of Texas in 1947. He received his B.D. in 1950 and his Th.D. in 1955, both from the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. In 1961, he began teaching at Duke University as Assistant Professor of Religion. In 1991, he published "The Moral Imagination and the Public Life: Raising the Ethical Question."
McCollough served as Director of Undergraduate Studies and Chair of the Curriculum Committee for the Department of Religion; he was Director of the Twentieth Century America Program, Chair of the Marshall Scholarship Committee, and served as a member to the Faculty Hearing Committee and FOCUS Advisory Board, having served as its first director. He retired from Duke University in 1997.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence, memoranda, minutes, course materials, and other papers and records with bulk dates 1983-1996. Major topics include the Department of Religion, the Twentieth Century America Program, and courses in ethics, community and public policy, along with materials concerning community service and related activities at Duke. While some files still contain student recommendations, student grades and social security numbers were destroyed.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Dept. of Religion.; Duke University. Faculty.; Duke University -- History -- 20th century.; Committees.
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - Dialogue/Chronicle Articles, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Duke Gardens "Flora" #1; DU Library Newsletter #2 and #22; AB
  - Duke Winners - 1979; Various Correspondence with Fein, Sanford, Cleaveland
  - UFCAS (Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences) minutes, 1989-1991
  - "Varieties of Learning Experience" - 1968 Publication by UFCAS
  - Fractional Course Committee - Memos, Minutes and Correspondence, 1979
  - TCAP (20th Century America Program) - Initial Program Institution, 1975-1978
  - TCAP - Evaluations Survey, 1987
  - TCAP - Rosters, David Price Info, Correspondence, 1987
  - TCAP - Rosters, Correspondence, 1988
  - Focus/TCAP - 1991-1997
  - BN Duke Scholarship, 1995
  - Honors and Prog II, 1965-1979
  - Honors and Prog II, 1991-1997
  - Majors - Religion Dept, 1965-1966
  - Religion Dept - Lon Range Planning, 1976, 1984
  - DUS Information - Course Proposals, Syllabi, Memos and Correspondence, 1990-1994
  - Curriculum Committee - Memos, Courses, Meetings, Agendas, Minutes, 1989-1992
  - Curriculum Committee - Memos, Courses, Meetings, Etc., 1992-1993
  - Curriculum Committee - Majors/Honors, 1994-1997
  - Religion Dept Correspondence - TEM, 1989-1990
  - Religion Dept - Memos from Chair, Handbook, Newsletter, Site Visit, Minutes, 1994
  - Religion Dept - Memos, Agendas, Minutes, 1995-1998
  - Barney Jones Endowment - Initial Campaign Info, Meetings, Correspondence, Chronicle Article, Fund Mailer, 1984-1996
  - Kenan Ethics Grant, 1995-1996
  - Habitat for Humanity, 1990-1996
  - Ethics Centers, 1994-1996
  - Non-medical Research Involving Human Subjects - Information, 1995
  - Ethical Issues and Social Change Public Policy, 1993-1995
  - Honor Commitment - Honor Council (Box 2)
  - Native Americans - Council of Energy Resource Tribes, 1992
  - L.E.A.P.S., 1994-1996
  - Community Service Center - Courses, Minutes, Task Force, 1990-1993
  - Fleishman - Ethics Colloquia, 1992-1993
  - Research Council - Correspondence, 1994
  - Laura Stepp - Washington Post - Correspondence and Faxes, 1992
  - Social Ethics / Human Development, 1991-1992
  - Zurich / Geneva Summer Program - Ethical Issues in World Health, 1991
  - Environment - School of Environment, 1992-1996
  - Student - Faculty Service Projects, 1988
  - House Course: Human Rights, 1990s
  - Women's Studies - Essays, O'Barr Correspondence, 1983-1985
  - Hunger Course, 1980-1982
  - Social Responsiveness of Business Symposium, 1982
  - Commonwealth Fund - Ethics and Medical Education, 1979
  - Residence Hall Design / Student Housing, 1983
  - Pre-Divinity Program - Summer II, 1982
  - Psychology and Ethics - Correspondence, Course, Survey, etc., 1967
  - Race and Ethics - Newspaper Clippings, Doug Adams Letter, c. 1967
  - Summer Session - Proposal, Memos, Notes, 1976-1977
  - Governor's Task Force - Humanistic Issues in Science and Technology, 1983
  - Round Table on Science and Public Affairs, 1979-1980
  - Leadership Program (PPS) - Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs, 1991-
  - Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs, 1976-1983
  - Proposal to Education Foundation of America, 1974
  - National Humanities Center - Flyers, Lectures, Correspondence, 1979-1980
  - Ethics and the Middle East (Gulf War) Articles, 1990
  - Program in Science, Technology and Human Values, 1985-1990
  - Summer Transitional Program, 1968-1969
  - Ethics House Course - Papers, Lectures, Syllabi, 1972, 1979, 1992-1995
  - International Studies, World Policies Institute, 1982-1984
  - Center for Study of Communications Policy, 1982-1986